A Guide to the Governor Henry Lee Executive Papers, 1791-1794
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor Henry Lee Executive Papers, 1791-1794
Library of Virginia
40611
4.83 cubic feet
Governor's Office
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 5048-5055.
Miscellaneous Reel 5048 - 1791 Dec.-1792 June 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5049 - 1792 July 2-Nov. 30 & Presidential Electors
Miscellaneous Reel 5050 - 1792 Dec. 1-1793 Mar. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5051 - 1793 Apr. 1-Aug. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5052 - 1793 Sept. 2-Dec. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5053 - 1794 Jan. 1-Apr. 29
Miscellaneous Reel 5054 - 1794 May 2-Aug. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5055 - 1794 Sept. 1-Nov. 30
Biographical Information
Henry Lee was born on 29 January 1756 at Leesylvania, Virginia. The eldest son of Henry Lee (1729-1787) and Lucy Grymes, he graduated from Princeton College in 1773. On 18 June 1776, Lee was commissioned by Patrick Henry as a captain of Virginia Light Dragoons in Col. Theodorick Bland's regiment, which was later attached to the First Continental Light Dragoons. The Continental Congress promoted Lee to major on 7 April 1778 and gave him command of three troops of horse, which became known as "Lee's Legion." Lee received a gold medal by the Continental Congress for his bravery in an attack against the British garrison at Paulus Hook, New Jersey, in August 1779. He served until the end of the war, having been promoted to lieutenant colonel on 6 November 1780, and meriting the nickname "Light Horse Harry Lee."
After the war, Lee married his cousin Matilda Lee, daughter of Richard Henry Lee, in April 1782. Matilda died in 1790, and Lee married Anne Hill Carter (1773-1829) from Shirley Plantation on 18 June 1793 and had five children, including Robert E. Lee. Lee began his political career as a representative of Westmoreland County in the Virginia House of Delegates, 1785-1786. Additionally, he served in the Continental Congress, 1786-1788, followed by a second stint in the General Assembly, 1788-1791. As a member of the Virginia Convention of 1788, Lee argued in favor of adopting the new federal Constitution. Lee became Governor of Virginia in 1791, serving three consecutive one-year terms. The most significant event of his governorship took place in 1794 when the Whiskey Rebellion broke out in western Pennsylvania. Given command the forces by President Washington in August 1794, Lee successfully led the army against the insurgents. Following his terms as Governor, Lee was again elected to represent Westmoreland County in the House of Delegates, 1795-1799. His last elected office was as a member of the Federalist Party in the House of Representatives during the Sixth Congress, 1799-1801.
Lee retired from public service and returned to manage his plantation at Stratford Hall. Financial hardships led Lee to debtor's prison in 1809. Here, Lee crafted his Memoirs of the War in the Southern Department. Lee traveled to the West Indies in 1816 to recuperate from illness, but died 25 March 1818 on his return at Cumberland Island, Georgia. Lee's body was re-interred on 30 May 1913 at Lee Chapel at Washington and Lee University in Lexington, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Governor Lee's Executive papers are organized chronologically with undated items arranged at the end of each year. These papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during Lee's three one-year terms as governor between 1 December 1791 until 1 December 1794. These records include correspondence written to James Wood who acted as Lieutenant Governor while Lee traveled to Nashville and again when he served as commander of the United States forces during the Whiskey Rebellion in 1794. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments for state positions; the Point of Fork Arsenal; defense of the frontier; the Whiskey Rebellion; resignations; arms & ammunition; Indian attacks; French emigrants; the Federal City; the Lunatic Hospital in Williamsburg; state expenses & revenue; quarantine of vessels; foreign affairs; Revolutionary claims; public tobacco; elections; Presidential electors; the Capitol Building; fortification of Alexandria & Norfolk harbors; the militia; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from Congress and the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; muster & pay rolls; accounts; oaths; pardons; receipts; election returns; election certificates; qualifications; lists; depositions; proclamations; petitions; reports; appointments; bonds; commissions; orders; reports; proceedings; applications; and other sundry items. Note that the pardons for 1792 have been separated to the end of the papers for that year.
Noteworthy correspondence originates from the United States government, Virginia State government, and miscellaneous sources. Prominent correspondents from the United States government include Henry Knox, Secretary of War; Thomas Jefferson, Secretary of State; Edmund Randolph, Attorney General; Alexander Campbell, District Attorney General; Thomas Johnson, David Stuart, Daniel Carroll, William Thornton, & Gustavus Scott, Commissioners of the Federal City; John Hopkins, Commissioner of Loans for Virginia; John Jacob Ulrich Rivardi, Engineer in the service of the U.S.; Samuel A. Otis, Secretary of the Senate; and the Virginia Delegates to Congress including James Monroe, Richard Henry Lee, and others.
Henry Knox, Secretary of War, corresponds the most frequently with Governor Lee from the United States government. Knox's correspondence primarily relates to Indian affairs and the defense of the frontier (1791 Dec. 5 & 24; 1792 Feb. 2; 1792 March 17; 1792 April 7; 1792 May 16; 1792 June 25 & 30; 1792 July 11; 1792 Sept. 15; 1792 Oct. 9, 11, 14, & 30; 1792 Nov. 1, 3, & 23; 1793 Feb. 16; 1793 May 16; 1793 July 25; 1793 Sept. 3; 1794 Jan. 27). In addition, Knox also writes regarding a variety of other concerns including: an escort for Governor Lee & Governor Pickens to Nashville (1792 Aug. 13), a treaty with the Indians north of the Ohio to be held at Lower Sandusky (1793 April 24), the defense of Norfolk (1793 May 10; 1794 March 19; & 1794 July 30), the capture of vessels in American waters by other powers & neutrality laws of the U.S. (1793 May 23 & 24; 1793 Aug. 21; 1793 Nov. 12; 1794 Feb. 11), money to the Commissioners of the Federal Buildings in Washington and the temporary residence of the President in Germantown, Pennsylvania (1793 Nov. 9), the recommendation of Daniel Bedinger to make gun carriages in Norfolk (1794 March 24), the appointment of Maj. Rivardi by the President to fortify Baltimore, Alexandria, & Norfolk (1794 March 28; 1794 April 3; & 1794 June 9), the spoliation at Guadeloupe by the French privateer Preus and British prisoners on parole (1794 April 17), the St. Domingo Fleet, the embargo, letters of marque, etc. (1794 May 9), an act directing a detachment from the militia of the U.S. (1794 May 19), the arming of vessels belonging to the belligerent powers in the U.S. (1794 June 27), the vessel of the British Consul taken possession by Gen. Thomas Mathews (1794 Aug. 25), and an arsenal or magazine within Virginia for the U.S. (1794 Nov. 10).
As Secretary of State, Thomas Jefferson writes the Governor to transmit acts & resolutions of Congress. On 1 Feb. 1792, Jefferson transmits copies of an act carrying into effect a contract between the U.S. & the state of Pennsylvania, and an act to extend the time for settling the accounts of the U.S. with the individual states. He also writes regarding an act concerning certain fisheries of the U.S. & for the regulation and government of the fishermen employed therein, an act to establish the Post Office & Post roads, and the ratification by three-quarters of the legislatures of certain articles in addition to and amendment to the Constitution (1792 March 1). He transmits an act supplemental to the act for making further provision for the protection of the frontiers, an act establishing a mint & regulating the coins of the U.S., and an act for finishing the lighthouse on Baldhead at the mouth of the Cape Fear River in North Carolina (1792 April 10). Note that the original acts are no longer included with the above correspondence.
Edmund Randolph, U.S. Attorney General, & Alexander Campbell, District Attorney General, often submit opinions respecting various matters. On 24 June 1793, Randolph writes regarding the suit brought by the Indiana Company against the state of Virginia. A circular letter from Randolph, dated 1792 Oct. 10, relates to ships of war bringing in French prizes in violation of the 17th article of the treaty of commerce between the U.S. & France. Similarly, Randolph's letter, dated 22 Oct. 1794, relates to the complaints of Joseph Fauchet, Minister Plenipotentiary of the French Republic, concerning French prizes in U.S. ports. Campbell writes the Lieutenant Governor on 23 Aug. 1793 regarding an insult to the British Consul at Norfolk. He also provides his opinion in favor of a arming a privateer from Cape Francois (1793 Sept. 25). On 3 Dec. 1793, Campbell writes that provisions may be sold by a neutral people to either belligerent and that repairs of vessels for non-military purposes is permissible. He provides another opinion regarding accusations by the British Consul at Norfolk respecting violence against the Brigantine Ann at Yorktown. The British Consul also accused persons at Smithfield of fitting out a ship to serve as a privateer in the present war. Campbell explains that this would be a violation of the laws of the U.S. and require the Governor to arrest the offenders (1794 July 11). Lastly, Campbell provides an opinion in favor of a French schooner from Baltimore that arrived in Norfolk with a prize captured at sea (1794 Aug. 15).
Thomas Johnson, David Stuart, Daniel Carroll, William Thornton, & Gustavus Scott, Commissioners of the Federal City, write the Governor on several occasions regarding Virginia's donation for the Federal Buildings (1792 June 6; 1793 Feb. 7; 1793 Sept. 23; 1794 Jan. 30; 1794 June 26; 1794 Sept. 16; & 1794 Nov. 7). John Hopkins, as Commissioner of Loans for Virginia, also writes the Governor on behalf of these Commissioners (1792 Jan. 25; 1792 May 8; 1793 Feb. 13; 1793 Sept. 13; 1793 Oct. 29; 1793 Nov. 20; 1794 Feb. 7; & 1794 Nov. 28). On 12 March 1792, Hopkins encloses a letter from William Deakins, Treasurer for Federal Buildings, regarding the donation. Hopkins also writes with respect to the state debt subscribed to the loan of the U.S. by the act of 4 Aug. 1790 (1792 March 12).
John Jacob Ulrich Rivardi, was appointed temporary engineer in the service of the U.S. for the purpose of fortifying the ports and harbors at Baltimore, Alexandria, & Norfolk. Rivardi writes the Governor on 3 April 1794 &, enclosing a copy of his instructions from Henry Knox. These instructions provide an estimate of the expenses at Baltimore & Norfolk. On 9 June 1794, Rivardi encloses a plan of Fort Nelson and writes that drawings of the Craney Island defense are forthcoming (enclosure not included). He writes concerning his progress in Norfolk on 15 June 1794. On 11 July 1794, Rivardi forwards a map of the Elizabeth River (not enclosed) and a return of hands working at Fort Norfolk. Shortly thereafter, Rivardi encloses a plan on Craney Island (not enclosed) and a return of laborers employed at Fort Nelson (1794 July 19). John Vermonnet was later appointed by the War Dept. to fortify Annapolis & Alexandria. Vermonnet writes on 17 June 1794 that he selected Jones' Point for a battery in Alexandria.
Virginia Delegates to the Second & Third Congresses corresponded with Governor Lee intermittently throughout his tenure. On 20 Dec. 1791, James Monroe transmits the proceedings of Congress respecting the representation bill. Richard Henry Lee & Monroe also write on 14 Feb. 1792 regarding military claims of land, and for services & supplies not yet compensated. Richard Henry Lee's letter of resignation, transcribed by Samuel Coleman, can also be found (1792 Oct. 8). Samuel A. Otis, as Clerk of the U.S. Senate, often transmits the journals of the Senate to the Governor (1792 June 1; 1793 May 1; & 1794 June 1). Otis also writes requesting copies of Virginia's laws(1792 Nov. 12).
Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include Samuel Coleman, Assistant Clerk of the Council of State; Simon Morgan, Adjutant General; Wyatt Coleman, Keeper of the Capitol; James Wood, Lieutenant Governor; James Innes, Attorney General; William Hay, Robert Goode, & William Foushee, etc., Directors of Public Buildings; Charles Hay, Clerk of the House of Delegates; Humphrey Brooke, Clerk of the Senate; Capt. Elias Langham & Robert Quarles, Superintendents of the Military Stores, Arms, & Ammunition at Point of Fork Arsenal; various county lieutenants; Andrew Lewis & Hugh Caperton, Captains of Volunteer Militia; James Madison, Jr., President of the Board of Directors of the Lunatic Hospital in Williamsburg; Harry Heth, State Agent of Public Tobacco; William Davies, Commissioner of Virginia for Claims Against the United States, John Pendleton, Jr., Auditor of Public Accounts; and Jacquelin Ambler, Treasurer.
Samuel Coleman, as Assistant Clerk of the Council, communicates with the Governor frequently through the Council Office. Coleman mainly writes concerning military matters including the militia (1792 Aug. 2; 1792 Dec. 19 & 31; 1793 Jan. 9, 24, & 30; 1793 Feb. 2 & 7; 1793 March 29; 1793 April 2 & 9; 1793 May 7; 1793 June 4; 1793 July 3 & 9; 1793 Aug. 5; 1793 Sept. 4, 5, 14, 26, & 30; 1793 Oct. 4 & 29; 1793 Nov. 2, 4, & 20; 1793 Dec. 9 & 22; 1794 March 15 & 24; 1794 June 2; 1794 Aug. 1; 1794 Nov. 18 & 28), an examination of returns from the Point of Fork Arsenal (1792 Jan. 11; 1792 April 10; 1792 May 25; 1792 July 10; 1792 Oct. 15; 1792 Nov. 1; 1793 Jan. 10; 1793 Feb. 7 & 20; 1793 April 16; 1793 Aug. 6 & 15; 1793 Oct. 1; 1793 Nov. 5; 1794 Jan. 2; 1794 April 1 & 11; ), the pay & muster of scouts & rangers on the frontier (1792 Jan. 31; 1792 March 24; 1792 April 11; 1792 Dec. 5; 1793 Jan. 7; 1793 Feb. 7; 1794 Jan. 16), accounts on the books of the Foundry (1791 Dec. 8; 1792 March 21; 1792 Dec. 27), and claims for military service or supplies (1791 Dec. 10; 1792 Oct. 23; 1793 Nov. 7; 1794 Sept. 3). On 11 May 1792, Coleman requests an appointment as Adjutant General, the duties of which were already annexed to his current position in the Council. He again applies for the position on 1 Dec. 1792, however, Simon Morgan was appointed instead. A letter, dated 20 June 1794, from Morgan encloses general orders to the Division Generals of the Militia. Another letter by Morgan requests that John Stewart be appointed his deputy (1794 Aug. 22).
Coleman also corresponds with the Governor regarding the state of the Capitol Building. On 11 July 1794, he writes on the problems with the roof of the Capitol and includes a rough diagram. Wyatt Coleman, Samuel's father, was appointed Keeper of the Capitol in 1793, and too writes the Governor regarding the defective state of the roof (1794 July 10 & 27). His earliest letter, dated 1 April 1793, remarks on his duties and includes an account for hiring a person to sweep & clean the Capitol. Both Samuel & Wyatt also write requesting instructions of the Keeper of the Capitol (1794 July 16, 24, & 25). On 16 July 1794, Wyatt Coleman encloses a memo of broken windows on the Capitol. Samuel also provides a report on his father's behalf on 11 September 1794 urging repairs to the windows before winter.
James Wood, Lieutenant Governor, traveled to Ohio County on the western frontier in June 1792 for the purpose of making an arrangement of the volunteer militia and for entering into contracts for their subsistence. He writes the governor on 20 June 1792 providing a report of his mission. This letter includes proceedings of the Board of Field Officers of Ohio Co.; instructions to Capt. McMachan on augmenting his command; the bond of Archibald & Robert Woods to furnish rations to supply Capt. McMachan's Company; an order to the county lieutenants of Monongalia, Harrison, & Randolph to make returns; returns of Harrison, Randolph, & Monongalia; instructions to Capt. Lowther; and charges by John Davis against John Evans, County Lieutenant of Monongalia. He writes again on 14 June 1793 regarding the state of the frontier in the Monongalia District and encloses instructions to Capt. William Lowther.
James Innes, Attorney General of Virginia, provides his opinion for the Governor on several occasions. On 3 Jan. 1792, Innes confirms his opinion respecting requisitions from Governor Thomas Mifflin for the apprehension of McGuire & Brady. He again writes regarding this case on 12 March 1792. On 27 Feb. 1792, he writes that the bond & mortgage for the public loan made to the French emigrants in Russell County is properly drawn. Later, he certifies that the title to fifty-five thousand acres sold by Richard Smith to Monsieur Tibeauf in Russell County is valid (1792 Feb. 28). In 1794, Innes was appointed by the President on a mission to deliver communications to the state of Kentucky. Writing from Lancaster, PA., dated 20 Nov. 1794, Innes states that he holds no office of profit under the United States and encloses a letter to Gov. Lee from 14 Aug. and a letter to Lt. Gov. Wood from 3 Oct. In the latter, Innes notes that General [John] Marshall has agreed to discharge his duties during his absence. During Innes' absence, Marshall provides several opinions including the purchase & sale of lands for arrears of taxes (1794 Oct. 15), fines & penalties under the militia law (1794 Oct. 15), and the forfeiture of the commission of Elisha White as Sheriff of Hanover (1794 Nov. 28). Other correspondence from Innes relates to delinquent sheriffs (1792 Sept. 7), the ability of individuals to sue the state (1792 Nov. 10), the suit of the Indiana Company against Virginia (1793 Jan. 22), the duties of district attorneys in cases of escheats (1793 Jan. 29), mortgages on Holt Richeson's estate (1794 June 20), and the Buckingham Works (1794 Aug. 16).
William Hay, Robert Goode, & William Foushee, etc., Directors of Public Buildings, kept the Governor informed of the ongoing repairs to the Capitol. On 14 June 1792, the Directors enclose a copy of their proceedings concerning the contract with Moses Austin & Co. Their letter also includes resolutions, a letter from Hay to Austin regarding problems with the Capitol's roof, and a statement of the expense of wall pipes, plastering, & covering the Pedestal cornice. Robert Goode requests an advance of fifty pounds to complete the steps of the Capitol (1793 Sept. 12). On 8 October 1794, Hay asks for an order for John Collins & George Winston on account of their contracts. Similarly, on 8 Nov. 1794, he solicits the Governor for an order for John Hart, one of the undertakers of the work on the Capitol. Finally, on 17 Jan. 1794, William Hay submits his letter of resignation to the Governor.
Charles Hay, Clerk of the House of Delegates, and Humphrey Brooke, Clerk of the Senate, often submit legislation and qualifications of election to the Governor. Noteworthy legislation includes a resolution to transmit the act to appoint electors to chose a president & vice president (1792 Oct. 10), an act to provide more effectually for the collection of the public taxes (1792 Dec. 23), a resolution for the Public Printer to print copies of the act imposing a public tax (1792 Dec. 23), a resolution regarding temporary defensive operations for the protection of the frontier (1793 Nov. 6), a resolution for the affectionate remembrance of the militia in enforcing obedience to the laws of the United States during the insurrection (1794 Nov. 12), a resolution regarding the sale of the mace used by the House of Delegates (1794 Nov. 17), and a resolution regarding the request of the President that Henry Lee take command of the army raised for the purpose of suppressing the insurrection in western Pennsylvania (1794 Nov. 19). In addition, there are qualifications of election for John Taylor to replace Richard Henry Lee in the U.S. Senate (1792 Oct. 18), Henry Lee as Governor (1792 Oct. 25), Henry Tazewell as Judge of the Court of Appeals to replace James Mercer (1793 Nov. 6), Patrick Henry to replace James Monroe in the U.S. Senate (1794 July 10), and Robert Brooke as Governor to replace Henry Lee (1794 Nov. 20).
Capt. Elias Langham, Superintendent of the Military Stores, Arms, & Ammunition at Point of Fork Arsenal, writes the Governor regarding plans for a reduction of the expenses at Point of Fork (1791 Dec. 7), accounts of hirelings' wages (1792 Jan. 11), neglect of duty by contractors for provisions (1792 Oct. 19), appointment of his brother John Langham as contractor for provisions (1792 Oct. 23), the claim of David Ross (1793 July 7), fear of a slave insurrection at Point of Fork & the need for a permanent guard (1793 Aug. 3), an account of balance due him for his pay (1793 Oct. 3), and accounts of provisions furnished Point of Fork (1794 April 5; 1794 May 20; 1794 June 11; 1794 Aug. 28; & 1794 Sept. 19). On 4 April 1792, William Price applies to the Governor to replace Langham upon his resignation. Similar applications were also submitted by John Guerrant, Jr., and J.K. Read for Col. Samuel Richardson (April 9 & 10). Langham, however, remained in office for another year. He writes to the Lt. Gov. on 24 Aug. 1793 requesting the Board to postpone the appointment of a new Superintendent for 15 days. On 26 Oct. 1793, he states that Maj. Quarles has been appointed to succeed him as Superintendent. Langham requests a certificate by the Board regarding his service and the cause of his replacement. On 29 Nov. 1793, Langham complains of the conduct of his successor in the contractor's office. Langham also includes certificates by John Peyton & D. McLaughlan, along with a letter from his brother John Langham. Quarles letter in response to these charges can also be found in this collection (1793 Nov. 29).
Maj. Robert Quarles succeeded Langham as Superintendent of Point of Fork in Sept. 1793. Quarles's correspondence relates to returns of ordnance & public stores at Point of Fork (1793 Sept. 2 & 5; 1793 Oct. 1; 1794 March 31; 1794 June 30; & 1794 Oct. 4), the punishment of a guard for neglect of duty (1793 Nov. 18); a commissary for the post (1793 Dec. 20), a request for arms (1794 April 18), an increase in wages for his sergeant for issuing rations (1794 June 2), the death of his Armourer Robert Fowler (1794 June 3), the exemption of militia duty for his garrison (1794 July 28), rations for the wives of artisans & guards (1794 July 28 & Sept. 2), and an increase in his salary (1794 Oct. 1 & Nov. 14). Note that additional materials relating to the Point of Fork Arsenal can be found at the end of the collection. Included are additional correspondence, accounts & receipts, pay rolls of state guard & artificers, quarterly accounts of cash, and returns of ordnance, military stores, etc.